Charles Emerson Beecher Archives
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
Charles Emerson Beecher Archives
1888-1904
IZAR.001571
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
10
The archives of Charles Emerson Beecher, particulary those dealing with his work on freshwater mollusca.
Beecher, Charles Emerson, 1856-1904
Biographical Sketch
Charles Emerson Beecher (b. 1858, d. 1904), son of Moses and Emily (Emerson) Beecher, was born in Dunkirk, New York, on October 9, 1856. When he was a youth, his family moved to northwestern Pennsylvania and Beecher began collecting fossils from the local sandstones and shales. By the time he arrived at the University of Michigan (B.S. 1878), he had amassed a very respectable collection of fossil phyllocarids and freshwater unionids. Following his graduation from the University of Michigan, Beecher became a personal assistant to James Hall in Albany for 10 years, and then at the request of Yale's Othniel C. Marsh, he moved to New Haven to oversee the Peabody Museum's growing collection of invertebrate fossils. In 1891, Beecher was awarded his doctorate for his study on Brachiospongidae, an enigmatic group of Silurian sponges.
Although Beecher is best known for his work on trilobites, he really didn't specialize on any particular group of organisms. Instead, he was interested in biological systems, evolution, and the relationship between ontogeny and phylogeny. Beecher's promotion was rapid. He ascended to Professor of Historical Geology in 1897 and, on the death of Marsh in 1899, Beecher succeeded him as Curator of the Geological Collections, the informal Director of the Peabody Museum of Natural History.
Description of the Material
These papers include correspondence and manuscript related material.
Connecticut; New York; USA; Pennsylvania; Correspondence; Manuscript materials; Yale Peabody Museum; Yale University
- Correspondence, 1888-1904; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence to C.E. Beecher.
  - George Washington Tryon Jr. Correspondence. Correspondence from G.W. Tryon to C.E. Beecher., 1887; 001591
    - George Washington Tryon Jr. Correspondence. A letter from G.W. Tryon to W.B. Marshall, apparently forwarded to C.E. Beecher., 05 Dec 1877; 001592
  - Henry Augustus Pilsbry Correspondence. Correspondence from H.A. Pilsbry to C.E. Beecher., 1890-1892; 001574
    - Henry Augustus Pilsbry Correspondence. A letter from H.A. Pilsbry to C.E. Beecher informing Beecher he has received the collection of Amnicolidae and discussing other species., 14 Feb 1892; 001576
    - Henry Augustus Pilsbry Correspondence. A letter from H.A. Pilsbry to William B. Marshall, apparently forwarded to C.E. Beecher informing Marshall he is returning his Amnicolidae named., 18 Mar 1890; 001577
    - Henry Augustus Pilsbry Correspondence. A letter from H.A. Pilsbry to C.E. Beecher discussing fresh-water mollusca taxonomy and systematics., 1890-1892; 001575
  - R. Ellsworth Call Correspondence. Correspondence from R.E. Call to C.E. Beecher., 1886-1889; 001586
    - R. Ellsworth Call Correspondence. A letter from R.E. Call to C.E. Beecher informing him he is sending another group of shells. He encloses a list of said specimens. Beecher has made notes on the list., 04 Mar 1888; 001589
    - R. Ellsworth Call Correspondence. A letter from R.E. Call to C.E. Beecher informing him he is sending specimens (Amnicola, etc.) requested by Beecher., 05 Aug 1886; 001587
    - R. Ellsworth Call Correspondence. A letter from R.E. Call to C.E. Beecher informing him he will send the requested shells and he will draw the operculas of all the forms., 14 Nov 1889; 001590
    - R. Ellsworth Call Correspondence. A letter from R.E. Call to C.E. Beecher discussing a drawing by Beecher and informing him he is sending more requested specimens., 28 Aug 1886; 001588
  - William Healey Dall Correspondence. Correspondence from W.H. Dall to C.E. Beecher., 1887-1891; 001578
    - William Healey Dall Correspondence. A letter from W.H. Dall to C.E. Beecher discussing Rissoidae taxonomy., 04 Nov 1887; 001580
    - William Healey Dall Correspondence. A letter from W.H. Dall to C.E. Beecher asking Beecher if he ready to receive specimens of Tryonia clathrata to study., 06 Jul 1891; 001585
    - William Healey Dall Correspondence. A letter from W.H. Dall to C.E. Beecher informing him he is sending specimens of Hydrobiinae., 10 Jan 1887; 001579
    - William Healey Dall Correspondence. A letter from W.H. Dall to C.E. Beecher informing him he is sending some specimens of Amnicola and other species., 10 Nov 1887; 001581
    - William Healey Dall Correspondence. A letter from W.H. Dall to C.E. Beecher informing him he is sending some specimens of Amnicola and other species, and have found all on his list but three of the requested species., 15 Nov 1887; 001582
    - William Healey Dall Correspondence. A letter from W.H. Dall to C.E. Beecher discussing Beecher's results in his investigation in regards to V. papoidea. He praises the value of Beecher's work and makes some technical suggestions., 20 Nov 1887; 001583
    - William Healey Dall Correspondence. A letter from W.H. Dall to C.E. Beecher discussing morphology nomenclature of the teeth of the radula., 29 Nov 1887; 001584
- Manuscript/Research Materials, 1888-1904; Series II
  C.E. Beecher manuscript material related to freshwater mollusca.
  - Freshwater Gastropoda. Archival material related to Beecher's work on freshwater mollusca., 1888-1904; 001599
    - Freshwater Gastropoda. 12 cards. Each of a species of Amnicola, Bythinella etc. The cards contain radual formula for each species., 1888-1904; 001600
    - Freshwater Gastropoda. Handwritten description with radula formula for Amnicola dalli., 1888-1904; 001601
    - Freshwater Gastropoda. Numerous cards with radual formula, drawings etc. of various species of Amnicola, Bythinella, etc. Also there is a handwritten paper titled by Beecher as "Lingual Dentitions of American Fresh-Water Rissoidae.", 1888-1904; 001602
    - Freshwater Gastropoda. Handwritten description of Hydrobia n.sp. Includes radula formula., 1888-1904; 001605
    - Freshwater Gastropoda. Handwritten paper titled "A new Species of Planorbis" by Beecher. Plamorbis costatus., 1888-1904; 001606
    - Freshwater Gastropoda. 5 slips of tracing paper with figures of radula., 1888-1904; 001610
    - Freshwater Gastropoda. Numerous radula figures of Bythinella, Amnicola, etc., 1888-1904; 001618
- Slide Labels, 1888-1904; Series III
  C.E. Beecher slide labels.
  - Slide Labels. C.E. Beecher slide labels., 1888-1904; 001608
    - Slide Labels. 35 slide box labels? They contain species names (bythinella, Amnicola, etc.), localities, some citations and radula formulas., 1888-1904; 001609